<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A journal of the siege and taking of Buda by the imperial army (under the conduct of the Duke of Lorrain, and His Electoral Highness, the Duke of Bavaria,) Anno Dom. 1686 by Jacob Richards ...</title>
            <author>Richards, Jacob, 1660?-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13775</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12255030</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12255030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70936)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 158:8 or 499:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A journal of the siege and taking of Buda by the imperial army (under the conduct of the Duke of Lorrain, and His Electoral Highness, the Duke of Bavaria,) Anno Dom. 1686 by Jacob Richards ...</title>
                  <author>Richards, Jacob, 1660?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p. : coat of arms  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M. Gilliflower ... and J. Partridge ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties command"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buda (Hungary) --  History --  Siege, 1686.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:57370:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>I R</head>
                  <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
                  <p>HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57370:1"/>
            <p>A JOURNAL Of the SIEGE and TAKING of BUDA, BY THE IMPERIAL ARMY, (Under the Conduct of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and his Electoral Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi>) <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1686.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Jacob Richards,</hi> One of His Majeſties Engineers, who was appointed by the Right Honourable the Lord <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> Maſter-General of His Majeſties Ordnance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſerve in the ſaid Army, and who is now in the Service of the <hi>Venetians</hi> in the <hi>Morea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>M. Gilliflower</hi> at the <hi>Black Spread-Eagle</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and <hi>J. Partridge</hi> at the Poſt-houſe at <hi>Charing-Croſs.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57370:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57370:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Illuſtrious and High-Born PRINCE James Fitz-James, DUKE of <hi>BERWICK,</hi> EARL of <hi>TINMO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH,</hi> BARON of <hi>BOSWORTH,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS a True Relation of ſo Famous an Action as the Taking of <hi>BUDA,</hi> with a Journal and Faithful Accompt of the various Attaques and Succeſſes of the Impetial Armyes in each day during the Siege of that ancient City, muſt needs divert and ſurprize the Underſtanding of ſuch as are curious in Heroick Story, ſo, my Lord, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help my own Preſumption in thinking, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all Mankind this Peice, collected with Study and Obſervation, onely ought to throw it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at Your Grace's Feet, who, perſuing the Noble Chace of Glory, were pleaſed to be Eye-witneſs of all the enſuing Paſſages, and can beſt defend my
<pb facs="tcp:57370:3"/>Aſſertions from the Ridiculous Malice of ſuch as envy me, either for being preſent at ſo Glorious an Action, or for addreſſing its Hiſtory to ſo Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary a Patron.</p>
            <p>Amongſt all thoſe, that through a Noble Thirſt of Fame voluntarily offer'd themſelves to ſhare the danger that muſt inevitably attend ſo difficult an Enterprize, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Heroe was ſtill moſt Obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; for Your Grace was ſo far from ſecuring Your Perſon and Obſervations by a diſtant Remarque, that the Royalty of Your Courage would often precipitate You to the common Accidents of the Mercenary Vulgar, not valuing the Hazard of Your Perſon amongſt the Hated Trunks of <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> nor the trembling Hearts of ſuch as honour'd You too much not to fear the fatal conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of ſo many dangerous, though brave, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures.</p>
            <p>No Attacque was ever made, to Mine ſprung, no Battery mounted, nor no extraordinary Exploit deſign'd, but ſtill Your Grace, either in Perſon, or in Will, was preſent, not confidering how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commonly eager each <hi>Barbarian</hi> would have been, to have pick'd out the Flower of all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Cavalry, the Blooming <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the very Soul of Valor, Royalty, and Honour, and by one hallowed Shot to have ſacrific'd him to his Moody Prophet, the ridiculous Impoſtor, <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met:</hi> But Your Guardian Angel, my Lord, that
<pb facs="tcp:57370:3"/>well knew the unvalued Treaſure committed to his Charge, and the glorious Character You were hereafter deſign'd by Providence to have in the mighty Records of eternal Fame, made the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Deſtinies ſtand aloof, encouraged by the Martial Fire ſtill glittering in Your Eyes, and the Reſolure Efforts of a Courage, that bravely ſhew'd the difference between the Sacred Blood of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, and the ſubjected Cement of the grovel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Vulgar, alluding, comparatively, Your Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour with that of Your Mighty Father, when the Poet addreſſing himſelf to Him, amongſt the reſt of his Lines, relating His Character, ſaid thus:
<q>
                  <l>Braveſt in Danger, Valiant, but not Raſh,</l>
                  <l>For when the <hi>Belgian</hi> Streamers brav'd the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Croſs,</l>
                  <l>Then on the bloody Deck. He ſeem'd to grow,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt Fate affrighted, and the Shot too low,</l>
                  <l>Aw'd with the Terror of His dauntleſs Brow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> This, my Lord, without Flattery, I ſay, I may very well allude to Your Grace's Behaviour at the Siege of <hi>BUDA,</hi> for whoever had ſeen with what a bluſhing Conſtancy, and preſence of Mind, You faced the worſt of Dangers, which Thouſands about Your Perſon could not remarque without the ſevereſt apprehenſions of Fear, would have thought there muſt be ſome Divinity about You, as
<pb facs="tcp:57370:4"/>well as Natural Courage, to ſupport the Diſtreſs of ſo many Eminent Hazards to which You daily expos'd Your Perſon.</p>
            <p>Nor do's Your Grace's excellent Character only extend itſelf to Arms and Glory, but branches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Confines of Induſtry and Ingenuity: And You are equally Renown'd for Your love to Arts as well as the other, thus proving the Royal Nature of Your moſt Auguſt and Invincible Father, who has ever ſmil'd upon the Endeavours of ſuch as ſtudy the Mathematicks, or any other Science con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the Benefit of His Kingdoms and Covem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and has likewiſe ſhewn the greateſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to them of any of His Royal Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors. And as, my Lord, I am extremely ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the Virtues that clearly ſhine through all Your Actions, ſo now I cannot doubt a Pardon for my Ambition in Dedicating to Your Grace this my Labour, and humbly begging to be receiv'd amongſt the Number of Your Admirers, and a Toleration to ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
               <signed>YOUR GRACES, <hi>moſt Humble, moſt Devoted, and moſt Obedient Servant,</hi> JACOB RICHARDS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57370:4"/>
            <head>A JOURNAL Of the Siege and Taking of BUDA, BY THE Imperial Army, (Under the Conduct of the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and his Electoral Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1686.</head>
            <p>FIeld Marſhal Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> with the Imperial Foot, and a Party of Horſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="June 15."/>(amounting together to Thirteen Thouſand Men,) came to <hi>Wehel</hi> on the <hi>Danube,</hi> where the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was Encamp'd with the Horſe. We continued in this Place all Night in ſight of <hi>Buda,</hi> the Horſe with a ſmall Body of Foot ever keeping One days March before the Foot and Baggage.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57370:5"/>
            <p>The Horſe and Foot decamp'd and march'd by favour of the Hills within reach of the Cannon of <hi>Buda.</hi> Count <hi>Staremherg</hi> halted here: But the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> march'd over the Hills to the Valley of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> where there is a a Way that leads to <hi>Alba Regalis.</hi> Here his Highneſs left a party of Horſe to hinder the <hi>Turks</hi> Intelligence from abroad.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bavarians</hi> with about 16 or 17000 Horſe were encamp'd on the Eaſt-ſide of the <hi>Danube;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17, 18."/> At their arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val 400 <hi>Turks</hi> who were in <hi>Peſt</hi> made a Sally, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately retired with the loſs of 8 Men, and fled into <hi>Buda.</hi> In their Retreat they broke the Bridge, leaving <hi>Peſt</hi> to us undamag'd.</p>
            <p>Nothing remarkable occurr'd,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19, 20."/> the <hi>Turks</hi> firing only a few random Shot at ſome Baggage that paſs'd over the Hills, but without Effect. The 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, arriv'd ſeveral Boats down the River with Ammunition. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> have now finiſh'd their Bridge of Boats over the <hi>Danube,</hi> which they have paſs'd, and march'd over the Hills where the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was. It is concluded, that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s Attack ſhould be at the North-End of the Town, and the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi>'s at the South, and accordingly the Army is divided, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> having 3000 Horſe, and 9000 Foot, 16 pieces of Cannon, 12 Mortars, with 15000 Bombs, Carcaſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Early this Morning the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> began their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches at about 500 Yards diſtance from the Wall of <hi>Lower Buda,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> making uſe of their old Trenches. They began at the firſt Baths of <hi>Old Buda,</hi> and continued paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel with the Town to the top of the Hill, where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn with a ſmall Eſpaulment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in the Plan. All
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57370:5"/>this Day and Night they continued their Works. In ſome places the Earth is ſo bad, that they are forc'd to make the Parapet of their Trenches with Faſſines and Baskets fill'd with Earth. The Enemy fir'd at us conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, but without damage. This Morning, about 8 of the Clock, our Foragers return'd without Forage, and brought News, that a Body of <hi>Turks</hi> appear'd on the Hills that lead to <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> and that they could not Forage without a good Body of Horſe to cover them; upon which, General <hi>Palfie</hi> was commanded out with a Body of 12000 Horſe, and march'd towards <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> to face the <hi>Turks.</hi> About 10 of the Clock, a <hi>Pole,</hi> who was taken at the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> made his Eſcape with the Baſſa's Horſe, Two Cemiters, and his Commanding Staff. He reports, that our Arrival before <hi>Buda</hi> was very ſurprizing. That the Gariſon is not half ſo ſtrong, as when the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians laid Siege to it in the Year 1684. when it conſiſted of 15000 Men, and now not above 7000. <hi>viz.</hi> 3000 Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, 1000 Horſe, 1000 Jews, and about 2000 Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants. That the <hi>Turks</hi> had Intelligence, the Chriſtians de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to beſiege <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> and <hi>Erla,</hi> which was true, it not being concluded to attempt <hi>Buda</hi> till the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> when at a General Council of War, held at <hi>Comorra,</hi> it was Reſolv'd.</p>
            <p>The Approaches were continu'd with Succeſs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> and a Battery rais'd againſt the <hi>N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Port.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> kill'd 8 Horſemen that were plac'd behind a Hill, to ſuſtain the Pioneers in caſe of Sallies.</p>
            <p>At Break of Day the Battery was finiſh'd,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> and the Cannon mounted, which were ply'd againſt the Wall of the Lower Town, juſt againſt the <hi>N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Port.</hi> About 7 in the Morning a <hi>Janiſary</hi> made his Eſcape out of the Town, and ſurrender'd himſelf upon a Dream the laſt Night, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57370:6"/>the Chriſtians would become Maſters of the Place, and put all to the Sword, as they had done the laſt Year at <hi>New-Heuſel,</hi> and that if he ſhould flie to the Chriſtians, he might find Mercy. He ſaid, the Gariſon was not above 6000 ſtrong. The Battery aforeſaid, conſiſting of 6 Pieces of Cannon, was ſo well Ply'd, as to make a Breach in the Wall of the Lower Town about 15 Paces broad, the Wall being about 5 Foot thick. This day two <hi>Turks</hi> appear'd on the ſide of <hi>Peſt,</hi> and attempted to ſwim over to <hi>Buda,</hi> which they could not perform, but return'd towards <hi>Erla,</hi> (the ſuppos'd Place they came from.) Several of the Gariſon defil'd out of the <hi>N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Port,</hi> in expectation of our giving the Aſſault this Night. A Party likewiſe came to defend the Breach, upon which a Detachement of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadiers were ſent to moleſt them. We continue our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches all this Night, without Impediment from the Enemy.</p>
            <p>We had Intelligence,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> that ſeveral <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Women em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd from <hi>Buda,</hi> with a deſign to paſs down the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nube</hi> towards <hi>Belgrade,</hi> upon which 400 Huſſars were ſent after them in two Boats, who Boarded and Took them: They were of the Baſſa's Family, who had ſent them with his Treaſure towards <hi>Belgrade.</hi> The Booty amounted to 10000 <hi>l.</hi> beſides what the Women and Children will ſell for. This day a Party of Granadiers were commanded to diſcover the Breach if it were Acceſſible, who reported it was, upon which Orders were given for the Storm in the manner following: <hi>viz.</hi> Fifty Granadiers and a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to beat the Enemy from an Eſpaulment they had made to flank the Breach; After them a Lieutenant, and 50 Muſquetiers, to ſuſtain the Granadiers. Then followed an Engineer with 100 Pioneers, to make the Lodgment on the other ſide of the Breach, after which followed a Captain and 100 Muſquetiers to ſuſtain the Pioneers, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57370:6"/>laſt of all a Major and 300 Men as a Rear-guard, and to face the Enemy in caſe of a Sally. This was executed about 10 of the Clock at Night, but with that Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that had the <hi>Turks</hi> kept their Poſt, they might have cut them all off, but they retir'd into the Town, and kill'd only 2, and wounded 30 of our Men. We found nothing at all of Pillage, but 40 or 50 poor Horſes. The Engi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer made his Work in Form of a Horſe-ſhoe, the two ſides of which were flank'd from the Town. We expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Turks</hi> would have ſally'd upon us, but they were ſo far from that, as by their proceeding they thought themſelves ſcarce ſafe in <hi>Buda,</hi> making a great Fire over againſt the <hi>N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Port,</hi> that they might ſee if we attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any thing by Petard. They were very diligent at Night by ſhooting from their Batteries and Walls, but with little or no Effect.</p>
            <p>We continued Maſters of the Breach,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> and made our Lodgment capable of 100 Men. This day we made a Blind of Cannon-Baskets to communicate with the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches that were brought on from the Baths.</p>
            <p>We cut a Line of Communication behind the Blinds,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> and made an Eſpaulment from the outſide of the Wall of the Old Town, which flank'd all that ſide that leads to the Valley of <hi>St. Paul,</hi> to hinder the Enemy from attempting any thing on that ſide. About 4 in the Afternoon, a Body of about 200 <hi>Turks</hi> defiled out of the Town, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to diſturb our Pioneers; upon which Count <hi>Aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> (a very gallant Gentleman,) with about 100 Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetiers attacqu'd them, who immediately retired with the loſs of 20 Men; on our ſide there were 3 kill'd, and 4 wounded. This Night Orders were given out for carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a Line of Communication with the Tower on the Old Wall looking into <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley, and the Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57370:7"/>before the Breach. It was order'd likewiſe, that a Battery ſhould be rais'd Parallel to the Tower, capable of 12 Pieces of Cannon. About 10 of the Clock, Cannon-Baskets and Faggots were brought to the Tower, in order to the raiſing a Battery. The <hi>Turks</hi> attempted nothing more this Night, but firing both Cannon and Small-ſhot on our Workmen, without any effect. This day my Lord <hi>Mountjoy</hi> was hurt in the Eye by a Cannon ſhot from the Town, which graz'd amongſt Stones.</p>
            <p>We proſecuted our Battery.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> About 3 a Clock in the Afternoon, a Body of 200 <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Horſe ſally'd out into <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley, and gallop'd towards the Hills, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercept ſome Baggage that was going to the <hi>Bavarian</hi> Camp, but a Party of about 50 Horſe belonging to Count <hi>Taaff</hi>'s Regiment, who had the Avant-Guard, and being very well poſted by favour of a little Hill, (under the Covert of which, the <hi>Turks</hi> came briskly on) conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued at their Poſt, and waited their coming, and as the <hi>Turks</hi> came within Piſtol-ſhot of the top of the Hill, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd, and gave them a whole diſcharge of their Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, kill'd and wounded about 50 <hi>Turks,</hi> who, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, preſs'd on, but, a Party of 100 Muſquetiers haſtning from our Traverſe by the Old Wall into the Valley, they retir'd, and at the ſame time about 400 <hi>Janizaries</hi> came out of the Eaſt Port, and poſted themſelves under the Cannon, to make good their Retreat, and kill'd and wounded about 16 of our Men.</p>
            <p>This day,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> the Line of Communication between the Lodgment and Angle of the Wall looking into <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley was finiſh'd, and another Line prolong'd from the Angle and Side of the Old Wall, ſo as to flank and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover any Sallies, that may be made out of the Weſt Port, or Port of <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley. Nothing more occurr'd, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57370:7"/>that the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhot great quantities of Pebble-ſtones on our Pioneers, which wounded ſome.</p>
            <p>The aboveſaid Line was finiſhed,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> and Orders were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to place four Mortar-pieces againſt Night; About 2 of the Clock in the Afternoon, a Party of <hi>Bavarians</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted the taking ſome Sheep that were feeding in the Valley; upon which the <hi>Turks</hi> made a Sally, which the Voluntiers obſerving, advanc'd againſt them, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd ſo far, that the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> in Perſon, with his own Guards, went to ſuccor and bring them off. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> loſt a Lieutenants Colonel, two Lieutenants, and an Enſign, with about 20 or 30 of our Troopers. This Action of the Voluntiers has by the Generals been greatly cenſur'd, and poſitive Orders given, that no Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntiers ſhould offer to picqueer. This Night our 4 Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars began to play, which ſet Fire to a Church, but it was ſoon put out. The Turks continue to ſhoot Stones at us.</p>
            <p>Four <hi>Grecians,</hi> who were Slaves in the Town,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> having the keeping of a Flock of Sheep, were at Paſture with them in <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley, and being near the <hi>Bavarians</hi> fled to them, the whole Flock, which conſiſted of 800 Sheep, following them. Theſe People could inform us of nothing, but that the <hi>Turks</hi> were very hard at work in making Retrenchments. They likewiſe ſay, there was a Mutiny of the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> againſt the Baſſa. The <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſaries</hi> in the laſt days Skirmiſh carried in two Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, for which they demanded 10 Ducats each as their due, but the Baſſa gave them but 10 <hi>Groſſes per Head,</hi> which is 18 <hi>d. ſterling.</hi> We continued working in our Trenches, and are now Half-way between the Old Wall and that of <hi>Buda.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:57370:8"/>
            <p>Our Battery was finiſh'd,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="July. 1."/> and we began to Fire upon the Angle of the Round Tower, which looks towards <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley. At the ſame time the four Mortars play'd, and with ſo good ſucceſs, as to diſmount the Guns on that Tower, and our Cannon diſmantled the Wall for about 6 Paces. About 10 of the clock in the morning, a Turkiſh Boy made his Eſcape. He ſaid, that Proviſions began to be ſearee, and that our Bombs had kill'd many of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and had diſmounted the Cannon on the Great Tower. We obſerv'd the Enemy at work on the Eaſt-Port, to which place they had advanc'd a Spurr, and brought Gabions, as if they deſign'd to make a Battery there, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting we would attacque them on that ſide.</p>
            <p>Our Battery conſiſting,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of twelve 24 Pounders, was ply'd diligently upon <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s corner Tower, and the Tower next the North Port, making conſiderable Breaches in both of them, though not acceſſible, yet ſo, as to take the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence wholly from them. Several Carcaſſes have been ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſet Fire on the Town, but as yet we have not learn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with what ſucceſs. Laſt Night two Boats came up the <hi>Danube</hi> and got into the Town, they are ſuppos'd to be Engineers and Gunners that were in <hi>Erla,</hi> which we have reaſon to believe, foraſmuch as this day we receiv'd more Bombs than ordinary from them, and very nigh our Battery, one of which fell into our Trenches and kill'd two of our Men. This Evening the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> went over to <hi>Peſt</hi>-ſide, and gave Orders for making 2 Redoubts on the ſhore, and left a Flying Camp conſiſting of 600 <hi>Huſſars,</hi> to hinder the Enemy from ſuccour by Boat.</p>
            <p>We carry'd on our Trenches,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and took in a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, from whence we return'd with an Angle and Parallel Line with <hi>Buda,</hi> till we came to the Right-hand way go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57370:8"/>to North Port, at which 3 Lines met by ſavour of a Wall and deep Road, under which our Men were Cover'd. We mounted 4 Mortars more juſt by the former, which Play'd continually into the Town. Our Cannon have now made a conſiderable Breach. This day a Janiſarie deſerted, who inform'd us, that their Gariſon was weak, conſiſting of not above 2500 Janiſaries, 1000 Spahis, 1000 Jews, and about 3000 Inhabitants, Men, Women, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: That Proviſions were very ſcarce, that our Bombs and Carcaſſes had ruined many of their Buildings, one of which kill'd 12 Janizaries, as they were Relieving the Guard. We have advice, that the <hi>Brandenburgs</hi> were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 4 hours March of us.</p>
            <p>Orders were given to advance a Line,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> from the Place where the 3 Lines met, ſo as to Flank the outermoſt of them, and joyn the Wall of the Old Town looking into St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Valley, which was accordingly done, and a Place of Arms made of a Building capable to hold about 2 or 300 Men. Behind and Parallel to the Line, which went from the Building, and home to the Wall, was made a Cover'd Place for a Battery of 4 Mortars. The <hi>Turks</hi> Fired more this Night than ordinary. We are now within 50 Paces of the Breach, which with the Light of the Moon encouraged the Enemy, not to ſpare either Muſquet Ball or Stones, thô with no great Effect, we not loſing above 3 or 4 Men, and 5 or 6 wounded. About 3 in the Morning we were under ground, well Cover'd from the Enemies Fire and capable of maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Works, if they ſhould attempt to moleſt us. We now diſcover'd, that the <hi>Turks</hi> were making a kind of a Fauſſebray juſt before the Breach, whereof the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals being acquainted, did not however think it worth the while to diſturb them. About 8 of the Clock the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57370:9"/>finiſhing of the Banquets and enlarging of the Trenches was left to the Officers and Soldiers, who were Poſted there according to their method. About 3 in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, the <hi>Brandenburgs</hi> arrived on <hi>Poſt</hi> ſide, whither the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> went to ſee them. They Receiv'd his Highneſs with 3 Salutes of Ordnance, ſmall Arms, and ſeveral Bombs and Carcaſſes. His Highneſs immediately allotted them their Quarters, and in what place they ſhould carry on their Attacque, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iz.</hi> on our Left, which was accordingly done, they Poſting themſelves by favour of the ground, where they were well cover'd from the Town. About 8 at Night a Serjeant and 10 Granadiers were ſent to the Breach to diſcover what the <hi>Turks</hi> were doing, whom they found Mining towards us, upon which Orders were given to advance a Counter-Mine from the 2d Traverſe and inſide of the Old Wall, looking into St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Valley, towards the <hi>Turks,</hi> with directions that if the Miners ſhould meet with the <hi>Turks</hi> Mine, to Vent it, otherwiſe to advance under the foot of the Wall, and then make the beſt uſe we could of ours.</p>
            <p>About 8 of the clock in the Morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> our Miners were about 20 foot under ground. The Battery of 4 Mortars is fixed, and begins to play, by ſlinging great quantities of Stone into the Town. The <hi>Brandenburgs</hi> have advanc'd 2 Parallel Lines, Communicating with ours on the Left; They loſt a Captain, 2 Lieutenants, and 10 Men, beſides their General's Son, who was ſitting in their Trenches, and diſcover'd by 2 Janiſaries to be a Man of Note, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching by the advantage of ſome ruines ſhot him dead. We continue Plying our Artillery, which about 9 at Night ſet Fire to the <hi>N: W:</hi> part of the Town, which continued very great till towards Morning. It's believ'd, we burnt at this time near half the Town.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57370:9"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6, &amp; 7."/> The <hi>Brandenburgers</hi> have joyn'd us with theſe 2 laſt days Trenches. We are now within 30 Paces of the foot of the Wall. The firſt Mine is quitted, and 2 more begun in the laſt approaches. We have added 2 more Mortars to the Batterye in the Lower Town. For theſe 2 days paſt nothing Extraordinary has hapned, except a Bomb of the <hi>Turks</hi> which fell into our Battery of Twelve 24 Pounders, which ſet fire to a Barrel of Powder, kill'd 2 Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and 4 Matroſſes, which was repaid them, by ſetting their Town on fire in ſeveral places, and killing with our Bombs and Carcaſſes above 500 of the Enemy, (as a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerter reports,) the <hi>Turks</hi> having diſmounted the <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> Battery, which has been ſilent theſe 24 hours.</p>
            <p>We found,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> that the Battery of the <hi>Swabiſh</hi> Hill did not the Execution was propos'd, the Cannon not carrying home, upon which it was order'd, that 5 Guns of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fire-Maſter's invention ſhould be plac'd on the ſame Hill, and the other taken away, which accordingly was done; they play'd into the Breach, and between the two Walls, incommoding the <hi>Turks</hi> very much, the Town lying open to the Hill. It rain'd very hard all this Night.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> About 4 in the Morning the <hi>Turks</hi> ſprang one of their Mines, which choak'd ours, in which were ſeven Miners, after which they Sally'd out in great numbers; About 400 fell in between the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgers,</hi> the later of which retir'd before we had the Alarum, ſo that we came by the worſt on't; We loſt in this Action above 150 Men, a Lieutenant Colonel and ſeveral other Officers. The <hi>Turks</hi> retired without doing harm to our Works with the loſs of Ten Men, whoſe Heads were ſet on the top of the Breach. It was expected, they would have made another Sally, for which every body was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57370:10"/>and matters ſo order'd, that they ſhould have been cut off in their Retreat. This Night, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars were fix'd on the Left, and ſomwhat behind our Battery looking into St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Valley. Our Bridge is broken down by a ſtorm.</p>
            <p>News was brought,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> that 6000 <hi>Turks</hi> was ſeen off of <hi>Erla,</hi> and were within 4 <hi>Hungarian</hi> Miles of us, upon which the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> Order'd General <hi>Commercy</hi> with a party of 3500 Horſe to March that way to face the Enemy, and cover our Foragers; Likewiſe 1000 Foot and 500 Horſe were Poſted on <hi>Peſt</hi>-ſide to cover and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure our Bridge, at the Head whereof they are now En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd. Ours and the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> Trenches are advanc'd home, and joyn'd towards the Left, in which the <hi>Brandenburgers</hi> have plac'd a Battery of ſix 24 Poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, likewiſe towards the Left have rais'd one of three 24 Pounders, both which play croſs-ways on the Paliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> The <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> towards <hi>Erla</hi> retir'd upon our advancing. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Fire-Maſter has ſhot ſeveral Bombs out of his Mortars, which threw them extraordinary high. We obſerve, that the Bombs flung out of his Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars very rarely brake, which is imputed to the depth the ſhell ſinks into the Earth, which ſtifles the Fuze. We are now compleating our Trenches, and advancing our 2 Mines. That under the middle Tower is 8 foot under the Wall, and will be ready to be charg'd in 24 hours. The <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgers</hi> have now compleated their Battery of 22 ſmall Guns for the ſhooting of Red-hot Iron Bullets. It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind and ſomwhat to the Left of our Platform of Twelve 24 Pounders. It has play'd all this day, but we don't yet perceive any Effect thereof. They have likewiſe erected a Battery of Howits, on the Left of their other Battery,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57370:10"/>but more under the Wall of the Lower Town: Theſe Howitts are mounted on Carriages ſomwhat reſembling thoſe of Cannon, the body has the form of a Mortar's, but a much longer Chamber and Chace, and is more forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by the Trunions, than at the Breech and Muzzle. They ſhoot out of them a Bomb fill'd with Combuſtible Compoſition, which I believe may be of good effect.</p>
            <p>Early this Morning, the Enemy ſprang another Mine,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> which likewiſe choak'd ours, blew up part of the middle Tower, and has ſhaken it very much: We have now began one towards the Moſque, juſt on the Left of the ſame Tower, and another on the Right towards St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Valley. I am off opinion, they do not ſink their Sap deep enough, and that the <hi>Turks</hi> in Counter mining have a great advantage, by being always undermoſt, which they certainly have been, otherwiſe they would have weakned their own Wall, and made paſſage for us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> This Morning 2 Engineers and 2 Officers were ſent to diſcover the Breach, which they reported to be acceſſible, upon which his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> reſolv'd, that a Lodgment ſhould be made thereon, and every thing was order'd accordingly. The Cannon and Mortars play very ſmartly all day to break the Paliſadoes on the Top of the Breach; The time appointed was 8 at Night, and the Aſſault to be on this manner, <hi>viz.</hi> a Captain and 50 Granadiers were to mount the Tower on the Right, and a Captain and 50 Granadiers to mount the middle Tower on the Left; After that, each Barty was to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd with a Captain and 50 Muſquetiers, then 2 Engi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers, a Sub-Engineer, and an Undertaker, accompany'd by 100 Pioneers each, to go to the Right and Left of the Breach, and theſe to make two Lodgments; Then were 2 Lieutenant Colonels and 500 Men to ſuſtain theſe, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57370:11"/>as many more ready, and under Arms to ſuſtain them. The Sign was to be the Quick Diſcharge of Artillery, which being given, the Granadiers mounted, but the <hi>Turks,</hi> having ſome intelligence of our purpoſe, receiv'd us with great Fire of Muſquets and Granadoes, and an infinite quantity of Stones. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Voluntiers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and a few <hi>French,</hi> were in this Action; Thoſe that went to the Left were, after a ſmall Diſpute, beaten off, by the ſpringing of a Fugade. The Engineers and Pioneers, inſtead of going to the Right and Left, fix'd in the middle of the Breach between the Fires of the two Towers, they had neither Sand-Sacks, Gabions, nor Cask, nor above 40 Fagots to make this Lodgment, and in this Confuſion continued there in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber about 3 or 400, for the ſpace of three quarters of an hour, without being able to gain the Paliſadoes. The <hi>Turks</hi> ſeem'd once to give way, but finding we did not advance, return'd upon us more vigorouſly, and ſpared neither Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet Ball, Granadoes, Lances, Arrows, nor Stones. Theſe flew like Hail, and kill'd us more Men than any thing elſe. At laſt we retir'd, which the <hi>Turks</hi> ſeeing, ſally'd out at the Port where the <hi>Brandenburgers</hi> were entren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, who receiv'd them ſo well, that they retir'd with the loſs of 18 Men, whoſe Heads were put up on their uppermoſt Line: What Men we loſt is not yet known; Among the <hi>Engliſh</hi> there was Captain <hi>Rupert,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> Mr. <hi>Moore,</hi> and Captain <hi>Talbot</hi> kill'd; Colonel <hi>Forbes,</hi> Captain <hi>St. George,</hi> Captain <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> and my Lord <hi>Savile,</hi> wounded by Muſquet ſhot, beſides ſeveral others hurt with Stones.</p>
            <p>After our Dead were carry'd off,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> a Liſt was given in to his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> of the kill'd and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>viz.</hi> 1000 Soldiers, beſides Officers, 50 Voluntiers, moſt of which are Noblemen, the reſt of the day was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57370:11"/>employ'd in burying the Dead. The <hi>Turks</hi> continued their Colours flying on the top of the Breach.</p>
            <p>Orders were given for enlarging the Trenches next the Breach, they being found in the Aſſault too ſtreight,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> and the cauſe of a great deal of Confuſion. This day Letters were intercepted from <hi>Hamet</hi> Baſſa to the Baſſa of <hi>Buda,</hi> bidding him be of Courage, for that he would certainly come to his Relief. About 4 in the Afternoon, we heard the <hi>Turks</hi> at work, juſt on the Right of our Left Gallery, going from the Moſque, upon which we began another on the Right of the Moſque, with intention to obſtruct them if upon a Level with us, and continued the other alſo. The <hi>Brandenburgers</hi> have play'd ſo hard on the Left of the Round Tower, that it is quite demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd.</p>
            <p>We pierc'd the Wall of the Lower Town looking into <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley, and carry'd on a 3d Angle Salliant,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> and rais'd a Battery of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Guns on that ſide which regards the Round Tower, which have been well ply'd, and with ſo good Succeſs, as to have ruin'd its Defence looking into the Valley, which annoy'd our Men in the Line of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travallation, and Communication, which we are carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on in the ſaid Valley to join the <hi>Bavarians</hi> on the other end of the Town, who have now lodg'd themſelves on the top of the Breach by the advantage of two Mines which they ſprang, in which Action they loſt but 12 Men.</p>
            <p>Early this morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> another Battery of Mortars was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Lower Town; The Captain of the Battery is a little Man, who formerly loſt both his Hands by the charging of a Cannon, which was not well ſpung'd. He is eſteem'd a knowing Man in ſhooting of Bombs, and other artificial Bodies. Amongſt others, his throwing 14
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57370:12"/>or 15 Hand-Granadoes at once out of a Mortar. This day a <hi>Turk</hi> fled to us, and reports, that they loſt above 500 Men in the laſt Aſſault; Likewiſe that their Vaults could not reſiſt the Force of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Bombs, one of which falling through an Arch, kill'd and wounded 80 Men, Women and Children. Our greateſt Talk now, is of a ſpeedy Battel with the <hi>Turks,</hi> who advance towards us apace. We have about 6000 Horſe on <hi>Peſt</hi> ſide, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd there for the Security of our Bridge, and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Succors to the Town by Boats. This Night the <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> ſprung a Mine, and made themſelves Maſters of the Fauſſebray the Enemy had made at the foot of the Ron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del.</p>
            <p>Early this morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> the <hi>Bavarians</hi> poſted themſelves at the Foot of the Breach, with the loſs of a Lieutenant-Colonel, and 30 or 40 Men. News came to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> that an Army of <hi>Turks</hi> appear'd on this ſide the <hi>Danube,</hi> upon which our Guards were doubled, but it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved falſe. The Horſe the next day were order'd to march that way. The Enemy was expected, upon advice that the Grand Viſier was marching towards us with an Army of 40000 Men. This day Mr. <hi>Kerr,</hi> a <hi>Scotch</hi> Gentleman, was kill'd in the Trenches.</p>
            <p>We added more Cannon to our Batteries,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20. &amp; 21."/> and ply'd them inceſſantly on the two Flanks of the Round Tower, which incommoded us ſo much in our laſt Attacque.</p>
            <p>About break of day the <hi>Turks</hi> ſally'd on the <hi>Bavarian</hi> ſide ſo vigorouſly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> as to beat them quite out of their Lines; kill'd a <hi>Saxon</hi> Colonel, the Colonel of the Artillery, and above 150 Men; Nail'd up a Battery of Cannon and 2 Mortars, and ſo retir'd, overturning their Gabions, and all without any conſiderable loſs. About an hour after the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57370:12"/>Enemies principal Magazine blew up, which ſtood near the Caſtle looking towards <hi>Peſt;</hi> The <hi>Danube</hi> is here above 500 Paces over, beyond which flew Stones of very great ſize. By this Accident a great part of the Wall was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with ſeveral other Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, went over to <hi>Peſt</hi> ſide to obſerve the Damage, which ſeem'd ſo great, that ſeveral were of Opinion we ſhould immediately ſtorm the Town in that place, but many difficulties ariſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That at that diſtance we could not diſcern, whether the Breach were acceſſible or not, and that our men would be greatly expos'd to the Cannon there. This Night a Deſerter came out of the Town, and reported they had loſt by the blowing up of the Magazine 1500 men.</p>
            <p>This day the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent a Letter to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Buda,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> which was deliver'd at the head of a Pike; as ſoon as it was read, the <hi>Turks</hi> hung out a white Flag on the top of the Breach, which caus'd a Rumor in the Army that they would Captiulate. There was a Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Arms on both ſides for the ſpace of 2 hours, during which time ſeveral of our men diſcours'd with the <hi>Turks</hi> in the Breach; This time being expired, 4 men were deſired to advance towards the Gate that leads to <hi>Alba Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galis,</hi> at which 4 Horſemen came out, one of them deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Viſier's Anſwer wrapp'd up in Sattin; at part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, one of the <hi>Turks</hi> preſented the Interpretation with an embroider'd Handkerchief. The Letter his Highneſs ſent imported, That he thought them not in a ſtate much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to reſiſt, that he was ready to give a General Aſſault, in which if they ſucceeded, they would be all put to the Sword, Man, Woman and Child, as at <hi>New-Heuſel;</hi> And that in Charity to ſave the effuſion of ſo much Blood, he gave them that Notice, that they might timely deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate for their Safety. This Letter the <hi>Turks</hi> anſwer'd
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57370:13"/>in three lines, viz. <hi>That they thought his Highneſs would juſtifie them, that they had hitherto done like brave Men, that they were reſolv'd to continue in ſo doing, that God puniſh'd the Vain-glorious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This day was deſign'd for a General Aſſault,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> but the Council being divided, and the <hi>Bavarians</hi> not ready, it was deferr'd. To day arrived about 2000 <hi>Heydukes</hi> and <hi>Huſſars,</hi> who encamp'd at the Head of Count <hi>Taaff</hi>'s Quarters on the <hi>Danube</hi> ſide.</p>
            <p>Early in the morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> the Rondel, which the <hi>Bavarians</hi> had batter'd at the Foot, fell, and the way into the Town or rather Caſtle made very paſſable. In the afternoon the <hi>Turks</hi> ſprang a Mine at the Foot of the Rondel, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Valley, and ſally'd out with about 50 Men, on that ſide, upon which our Men that were neareſt quitted their Line, and puſh'd them very bravely back. In the mean time they made another Sally on the Left, in a much greater number, falling upon the <hi>Brandenburgers,</hi> and cut ſeveral of them in pieces, who immediately ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying repuls'd them very ſmartly with equal loſs. A par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty likwiſe attacqu'd the <hi>Heydukes</hi> that were nigh the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, encamp'd under the Wall of the Old Town, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the <hi>Turks</hi> with great Cryes of <hi>Allah, Allah;</hi> Then the <hi>Heydukes</hi> rallying, puſh'd the <hi>Turks</hi> with great Cryes of <hi>Hida, Hida,</hi> and would be ſomtimes ſo mix'd, as one could ſcarce diſtinguiſh them. Thus the Skirmiſh continu'd for two hours, with the loſs of about 100 Men on each ſide. Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Arty</hi> was ſhot in the Leg.</p>
            <p>News came,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> that the Enemy approached, and had ſent 15000 Men to obſerve us, and attempt putting relief into the Town. Our Mines not ſucceeding, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to burn the Paliſadoes of the Breach by Artificial
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57370:13"/>Fire, in order to an Aſſault the next day. The Wind was favourable on the <hi>Bavarian's</hi> ſide, and burnt the Paliſadoes to the Ground, but on the <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſide the Fire would not fix, but did rather incommode ourſelves, both Fire and Smoak coming on our Lines.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> being reſolv'd to give a General Aſſault, order'd the Cannon to play very ſmartly on the Paliſadoes, which had very good Effect. About 4 in the Afternoon the Signal was given from the <hi>Swabes</hi> Hill by Cannon. The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> went on firſt, attacquing the middle of the Courtain, and the great Tower on the Right, where they were twice beaten off, before they could reach the Paliſadoes on the top of the Breach. At the ſame time the <hi>Brandenburgers</hi> and <hi>Heydukes</hi> attacqu'd the Tower on the Left, with a ſlow, but very firm pace, marching in Battalion, mounted the Breach, and fixed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on the top of the Paliſadoes, and maintain'd them, which the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> ſeeing, mounted the third time to the Paliſadoes, which many of them paſs'd, and having lodg'd themſelves on the Tower on the Right, mann'd it with their own Men, where they were no ſooner entred, but a Fugade overturn'd the whole ſurface of the Ron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del Men and all, which did not ſo diſcourage us but a ſecond Battalion took the Poſt, who were treated in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with the firſt by a lower degree of Fugades or Jorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aux, a third follow'd when a large Mine ſprung, which beat them off again, however this Poſt was repoſſeſs'd by the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> who maintain'd it with great bravery, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> all this while at the Foot of the Breach encouraging his Soldiers. The <hi>Bavarians</hi> likewiſe lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves in a Rondel, entred into a Court of the Caſtle, where was a Battery of 9 Guns and 4 Mortars; It was a <hi>Saxon</hi> Captain who firſt entred by a ſmall Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brazure, and finding the place very open, and overlook'd
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57370:14"/>by the Caſtle, nayl'd up the Cannon and Mortars, and ſo retir'd to the Lodgment on the Breach.</p>
            <p>Our Lodgment on the top of the Breach was now bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſecur'd,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> and a Parapet of Sand-ſacks made for the betetr covering of our Men; Likewiſe the ruins of the Breach made more eaſy for the coming and going to the top of the Lodgment, and the Fire put out of the Pali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadoes of our Lodgment, which the <hi>Turks</hi> had made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the quitting of it, which gave us no ſmall trouble. This day the Miners were fixed to the 2d Wall.</p>
            <p>We ſprung 3 Mines with no great ſucceſs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> yet they help'd to fill the Ditch, which was between our Lodgment and the 2d Wall. The <hi>Turks</hi> planted 2 pieces of Cannon in a high Steeple, which overlook'd all our Works, and kill'd many of our Men, upon which 3 Guns were pointed upon them, which were ply'd ſo well, that they were ſoon diſmounted, and the Tower almoſt beaten down. This day likewiſe a Scaffold was erected on the top of the Breach for a Platform of Guns. Two Mines more are begun.</p>
            <p>Proviſions of Cask and Sand-Sacks are order'd to be made and thrown into the Ditch.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> In the evening the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> with the concurrence of the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> ſent a ſecond Summons to the Town, by the Count <hi>de Lomberg,</hi> to whom the <hi>Turks</hi> reply'd, that an Anſwer ſhould be ſent the next day, it being too late then. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice was given us by ſome Boors of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> that the Grand Viſier was to paſs the Bridge of <hi>Effecke</hi> the 28th Inſtant, and that 6000 Men were march'd before, whom they left 18 <hi>Hungarian</hi> Miles off. Three Cannon are mounted on our new Lodgment, and begin to fire.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57370:14"/>
            <p>In the Morning, about 9 of the Clock,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> the <hi>Turks</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd an Anſwer to the General's Letter, letting him know, <hi>That the Town was in the hands of God, and that they could not give it up, but if they would receive another Place in lieu of it, they would Treat thereupon.</hi> But the General's Reply was, That his Imperial Majeſty had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him forthwith to Surrender, or never more to expect Offers of Capitulation. After this, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> order'd two Mines to be ſprung, which were ready under the ſecond Wall; That towards the Right deſtroy'd the Wall very much, but made little or no Breach through, but endamaged our new Battery on the top of the Breach. In the Evening, the Enemy ſent two Meſſengers to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> whereupon his Highneſs ſent two Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and there was a Ceſſation of Fire for about two hours. The Baſſa then propos'd to deliver the Town, if we would conclude a Peace on its Surrendry, which he ſaid he had power to do, urging the Advantage it would be to the Emperor. This was anſwer'd by the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> that he would do them what Service he could, but had no Commiſſion to conclude a Peace; upon this, the <hi>Turks</hi> return'd, and we renew'd our Fire. This day Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> was ſhot in the Hand and Neck, as he was looking through the Sand-Sacks on the top of the Breach.</p>
            <p>Two Cannon more were added to the Battery on the Lodgment,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Aug. 1."/> and our Mortars were brought nearer to the Foot of the ſaid Lodgment. More Cask and Sand-Sacks were ready for filling the Ditch. Our Horſes which were ſent to <hi>Alba Regalis,</hi> and the Bridge of <hi>Eſſecke,</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, bringing News of the <hi>Turks</hi> Approach.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57370:15"/>
            <p>We proſecuted the filling of the Ditch,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and Orders were given to the Engineers for tracing out our Lines of Circumvallation, which being once done is compleated by the Regiments, whoſe Officers take care to encourage and forward the Work, the Engineer reviewing the Works ſomtimes, that no miſtake be committed. All the Talk now is of the Enemy's advancing.</p>
            <p>Early this Morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> things were in a readineſs for a general Aſſault, which began on the <hi>Bavarians</hi> ſide, who, after a ſmall time, retired, finding the <hi>Turks</hi> too well bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricado'd and prepar'd for them, who were no ways fitted for the Enterprize, ſo they made their Retreat to their Lodgment with the loſs of about 50 Men; At the ſame time, a Mine was ſprung on the <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſide, which did nothing but ſhake the ſecond Wall, and throw a few Stones into <hi>St. Paul's</hi> Valley. The ill ſucceſs of this Mine had alter'd the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s purpoſe of making the Aſſault this day, but, upon the arrival of a Meſſenger from the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who brought word that they had begun and could not go back, his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> order'd a Party of Dragoons to quit their Horſes, and paſs the Ditch, which they very bravely perform'd, accompany'd with ſome Foot, in all to the number of 300 Men. The Deſcent and Aſcent was very difficult, ſo that the <hi>Turks</hi> had time to receive them very ſmartly. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> perceiving that this At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt would not ſucceed without a neceſſity of ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving them by freſh Men, and being loth to expoſe ſo many, in ſo open and large a Ditch, to Stones, Granadoes, Arrows, Bullets, and Fire-Trunks, and at the ſame time receiving advice that the <hi>Bavarians</hi> were retir'd, his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs order'd likewiſe a Retreat, but not half our Men
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57370:15"/>came back. We loſt in this Action two Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, and two Majors; General <hi>Megrett</hi> was wounded in the Foot by an Arrow, and my Lord <hi>Mountjoy</hi> in the Face with a Muſquet-ſhot.</p>
            <p>We advanc'd our Lodgment to the Tower on the Right,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> looking into <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley, and continued our Line of Circumvallation.</p>
            <p>We had News,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the Grand Viſier had not yet paſs'd the Bridge of <hi>Eſſecke,</hi> and that it was thought he would hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leave that Poſt, being very apprehenſive, that General <hi>Schultz,</hi> who commanded in <hi>Croatia,</hi> might fall upon it, and burn it, as General <hi>Leſlie</hi> had done formerly. We are likewiſe inform'd, that 6000 <hi>Turks</hi> are marching to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, to endeavour the putting Succor into the Town. In the Evening, the <hi>Bavarians</hi> diſcover'd a Gallery of the <hi>Turks,</hi> which they poſſeſs'd.</p>
            <p>This Morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> a Party of <hi>Huſſars</hi> brought in five <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Priſoners, who told us, that the Seraſquier was at <hi>Alba Regalis</hi> with about 20000 Men, and that by this time the Grand Viſier muſt have paſs'd the Bridge of <hi>Eſſecke</hi> with a much greater Force. This News made us work very hard to compleat our Lines, that the whole Army might be encamp'd within them.</p>
            <p>We continued working on our Lines,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> and to preſs our Miners in their Work under the ſecond Wall to blow away the Paliſadoes, which to us ſeem ſtronger and ſtronger every day. The News of yeſterday is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57370:16"/>
            <p>Early this Morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> ſome <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> appear'd on the Hill, having ſurpriz'd and cut off our advanc'd Guard of 100 <hi>Huſſars,</hi> upon which we ſounded to Horſe to receive them. They continued there about two hours skirmiſhing with ſome of our <hi>Hungarians,</hi> and ſo retir'd, and we return'd to our Camp. This day our Bridge above the Town was remov'd, being thought too far from our Camp, and another was made below the Town where the <hi>Bavarians</hi> were encamp'd.</p>
            <p>Early this Morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> we heard a great Noiſe towards our Trenches, much reſembling Shooting, which at firſt we thought to be ſome Sally of the <hi>Turks:</hi> It continued for a time, which made the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> haſten thither, where his Highneſs was told, that the <hi>Turks</hi> had thrown a Bomb amongſt a parcel of Hand-Granadoes, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber about Four thouſand, which made that Noiſe, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led two Men, and ſlightly wounded Count <hi>Archinto,</hi> who then commanded in the Trenches. Towards Noon, the <hi>Turks</hi> appear'd upon the Hills where they were the day before.</p>
            <p>Little of Moment occurr'd.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
            </p>
            <p>Our Miners reported to his Highneſs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> that their three Mines under the ſecond Wall were ready, upon which he order'd, that all things ſhould be prepar'd by the next Morning for a general Aſſault.</p>
            <p>Every thing was in good order by break of Day,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> and the Mines ſprung, which, like the reſt, had no other ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect than the killing our own Men, with which the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> was greatly diſpleas'd, ſaying aloud, <hi>'Twas well
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57370:16"/>Field-Battels depended not on Miners,</hi> and ſo order'd the Soldiers that were commanded to the Trenches, to retire to their Camp. The whole Army was order'd to march at eight of the Clock at Night to get over the Valley, and gain the Brows of the Hills which lie betwixt us and the Enemy, (on which the <hi>Turks</hi> were encamp'd,) and to fall on them at break of Day, but as we were ready to advance, News was brought that the Grand Viſier was arrived, and at the ſame time we perceiv'd their Camp to advance, and Fires kindled on the Deſcent of thoſe Hills we deſign'd to gain, ſo that we were all order'd back to our Tents.</p>
            <p>This Morning at eight of the Clock,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> the <hi>Turks</hi> Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to march down the ſaid Hills, as if they intended to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacque our Lines; The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> obſerv'd a Party to march towards our Right, as if they deſign'd to gain ſome Hills which commanded a great part of our Lines, and at that time the Right Wing of our Army; the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> apprehenſive of this, commanded the Army tor march out of the Lines, and made the Right Wing ſtretch to the very top of the ſaid Hills, making an even Front with the reſt, and ſo we continued in this Order, the Enemy ſtill advancing but very ſlowly. The Left Wing, commanded by the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> ſtood in their Lines which join'd the <hi>Danube,</hi> the whole Line was well furniſh'd with Cannon and Bombs under ground about 50 Paces from it. This Line is very complete, reaching from the <hi>Danube</hi> ſide in a very ſtrait Line croſs the Plain to ſome ſteep Hills, that are at this time cover'd with the <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> and other Auxiliaries, our Right Wing conſiſting of old Imperial Regiments which reach'd to the top of the ſaid Mountains, the general Form was one Squadron, and two Battalions, which Order was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57370:17"/>obſerv'd likewiſe in their Encamping, as may be ſeen in the Plan of <hi>Buda.</hi> The Battalions took up a great deal of ground to make a great Show, though very weak in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at this time.</p>
            <p>About five in the Morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> we perceiv'd the Enemy marching down again into the Plain with three or four great Detachments on their Left Wing, which ſeparated and march'd along the Valley to get behind the Hills which were on our Right, thinking to gain them, and fall on our Right Wing in Flank and Rear, in order to the putting Succor into the Town; but the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving their deſign, order'd ſeven Regiments of Horſe, and ſome <hi>Hungarians,</hi> under the Command of General <hi>Dunewalt, Taaffe</hi> and <hi>Palfie,</hi> to march up the Hills, and poſſeſs the top of them, facing the Enemy. We were no ſooner up, but immediately the <hi>Turks</hi> appear'd on our Left, who ſtill made towards us, there being a deep Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley between; preſently appear'd others on our Right where the Valley ended, their Body not being come up, kept skirmiſhing for the ſpace of an hour with ſome <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> when of a ſudden the Hills were cover'd with the Enemy, who immediately gave us a diſcharge of eight pieces of Cannon, and with terrible Cries fell moſt furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly on the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who immediately gave way, whereupon Count <hi>Taaffe,</hi> &amp;c. advanc'd, Mr. <hi>Fitz-James</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Voluntiers being in the firſt Rank. This Charge was perform'd with that Gallantry, that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my could not endure it, but immediately fled as faſt as they came on. We perſu'd them about a League, the way being ſo very bad for the Foot, that moſt of the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſaries</hi> were cut off, the reſt fled into the Plains, Buſhes and deep Hollows which lead into the Valley, where they had a great Reſerve, which made us halt, till the reſt of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57370:17"/>the Party were come up, who had made a great Circuit in perſuing thoſe, who fled into the Plains that lay between our Camp. From hence we obſerv'd the reſt of the <hi>Turks</hi> Army ſcatter'd like Flocks of ſheep. As ſoon as the ſeven Regiments had beaten the <hi>Turks</hi> on the Hills, his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs advanc'd his Right Wing from the Heights towards the Plain, the <hi>Brandenburgers</hi> and Auxiliaries quitting their Lines, and marching in good Order towards the Enemy, before the <hi>Bavarians</hi> (who were the Left Wing,) had got half over the Plain. The <hi>Turks</hi> Right Wing retires to the top of their Hills, which were very difficult of Acceſs, and there left a Party, and ſends the reſt to the Left Wing, which now is very hard preſs'd by General <hi>Taaffe</hi> and <hi>Dunewalt,</hi> which, with the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi>'s motion on the ſame ſide, gave the <hi>Turks</hi> ſome Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, they not ſtirring from the Foot of their Hills, we continued in our aforeſaid Order, galling them as much as poſſibly we could with our Field-pieces, at which time a Party of <hi>Turks</hi> attacqu'd very briskly the Left of our Right Wing, where a Party of <hi>Hungarians</hi> were poſted, who ſoon gave way, and had not General <hi>Taaffe</hi> with two or three Squadrons of Dragoons come up to ſuſtain them, (the Enemy having already forc'd our Line,) 'tis believ'd they would have endanger'd the putting Succor into the Town; ſhortly after, a Party was ſeen to detach from their Left towards the Right Flank of our Right Wing, which General <hi>Taaffe</hi> by a great Preſence of Mind perceiving, immediately commanded about four Squadrons of light Horſe to poſt themſelves at the Foot of thoſe Hills, which the <hi>Turks</hi> ſeem'd to preſs for, and by that means to have got into the Town. This Order of Count <hi>Taaff</hi>'s was perform'd with ſo much Expedition, that not above 20 or 30 <hi>Turks</hi> gain'd the Hill, who were cut to pieces. Our General now ſeem'd under ſome uncertainty, whether
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57370:18"/>to attacque the Enemy on the Hills, and puſh for an intire Victory, or return to our Lines, and proſecute the Siege, but the <hi>Turks</hi> ſeeming to retire, and conſidering how difficult the Aſcent was, and drow uneaſie to Horſe, (already ſo much haraſs'd,) how weak his Wing was, and how liable to be forc'd by an Enemy that charg'd with ſo much Fury, who had a Town in their view, and would be content to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice their whole Army to its preſervation, it was therefore thought moſt adviſeable to return into our Lines, and preſs on the Siege. The <hi>Turks</hi> loſt in this Mornings Action a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 3000 of their beſt <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> being all pick'd men to attempt our Line, and get into the Town by that unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected and difficult paſſage. We took about 500 Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, 58 Standards, and 8 pieces of Cannon. The Baſſa that commanded them was kill'd, and the Aga of the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſaries</hi> wounded; Mr. <hi>Fitz-James</hi> was in all this Action with Count <hi>Taaffe,</hi> behaving himſelf with Remarkable Gallantry. It pleaſed God, that neither he nor any of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Voluntiers had any hurt.</p>
            <p>This Morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> the Grand Viſier removed his Camp, and march'd back towards <hi>Alba Regalis;</hi> he ſtrangled the Baſſa who brought him News of their Defeat, and told him, <hi>That they charg'd us like Lyons, but were receiv'd by Devils;</hi> upon which the Grand Viſier ſpit in his Face, and commanded him to be diſpatch'd.</p>
            <p>Early this Morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Standards were plac'd on the top of our Breach, at the putting up of which the Enemy ſhot very warmly upon them, and kill'd ſeveral of our Men. This Night, his Highneſs order'd a burning-Comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſition of Father <hi>Gabriel</hi>'s to be fix'd to the Paliſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does, which burnt ſeveral of them, but before Morning the <hi>Turks,</hi> by unſpeakable Diligence and Induſtry, had pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced new ones.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:57370:18"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> An Attempt was made to take another Lodgment nearer the <hi>Turks</hi> Retrenchments, but we were beaten off with loſs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18, 19."/> We wrought at a new Battery in the Line of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallation, to take away the Defence, and diſmount the Cannon of the two Round Towers that look into <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley, which incommoded us much in paſſing and repaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the <hi>Danube</hi> ſide.</p>
            <p>At break of day,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> and juſt as our advanc'd Guard re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, 3 or 4000 <hi>Tartars</hi> and <hi>Janiſaries</hi> on Horſe-back, appear'd near our Lines in <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley, upon which the Trumpet ſounded to Horſe, but before our Men could mount, about 150 forc'd through, and got into the Town. Our ordinary Guards, which were about 500, entertain'd them for ſome time, till others came to their aſſiſtance, when they were repuls'd with the loſs of 200 upon the place, beſides the taking of ſeveral Priſoners, who told us that 2000 of theſe were <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> to whom the Grand Viſier had promis'd 20 Aſpers a day, during life, to all who entred the Town.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Orders were given for paliſading the Breach of the Lower Town, and all other Paſſages leading that way, and a Gariſon of 500 Men were put into the Round Tower by the Water-ſide. This day likewiſe our Battery of eight 24 Pounders began to play on the Round Tower looking into <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley, againſt which the <hi>Turks</hi> rais'd an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of ſeven heavy Cannon upon the Courtine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two ſaid Towers, which much incommoded us.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57370:19"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> The <hi>Bavarians</hi> lodg'd themſelves on the top of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle which they had ruin'd with their Cannon: That part of the Line of Contravallation was doubled, and a large Redoubt built at the Foot of the <hi>Swabes</hi> Hill, all which was well paliſado'd; likewiſe two Squadrons of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, viz. <hi>Mercie</hi> and <hi>Seraucte</hi> were poſted on the other ſide of the Hill, ſo as to give Check to the Enemy in caſe of a ſecond Attempt that way. This Night we had great ſtorms of Wind and Rain, which forc'd the <hi>Bavarians</hi> from their laſt Lodgment, which lay very high, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the weather.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> The <hi>Bavarians</hi> repoſſeſs'd themſelves of their former Lodgment. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> order'd a large Sap to be made into the Ditch which lay between our Lodgment and the two Walls, by that means intending to fill it up with Sand-ſacks and Barrels of earth. This Night we had Notice that the Enemy was to fall upon us, upon which we kept our Horſes all ſadled, and our Men alert, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hapned.</p>
            <p>About 10 in the Morning,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> the Enemy ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the Hills where they us'd to appear beyond the great Plain, and we ſaw their Camp ſome ſpace behind them. Our Army was drawn out to their old Poſt, but they not advancing, nor appearing in great Numbers, we return'd to our Camp. This day we batter'd the Town without Intermiſſion.</p>
            <p>A Deſerter came from the <hi>Turks,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> that ſaid they would attacque us the next day. This Evening the Beſieged diſlodg'd the <hi>Bavarians</hi> from their Poſt, which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain'd that Night with the loſs of 18 Men.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57370:19"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> We expected the Troops from <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> with great Impatience. A Battery of 8 Guns was plac'd to flank the Breach on the <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſide.</p>
            <p>A Boom was made croſs the River with pieces of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to prevent ſwimming into the Town.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> We had No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that General <hi>Scherffenberg</hi> left <hi>Zolnock</hi> but that day, (having ſtay'd there five days,) which was no ſmall trouble to us, and the more, becauſe a Deſerter aſſur'd us, that the Viſier had ſetled the attacquing us that very Night. That 3000 <hi>Janiſaries</hi> had 20 Crowns apiece to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind us, and throw themſelves into the Town, while with the Army he attacqu'd us that Night. All our Men kept their Poſt, and the General ſent 200 Wagons to meet General <hi>Scherffenberg</hi>'s Foot, to bring them forward with the more Expedition.</p>
            <p>We yet ſee no Enemy, nor any Succor,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> though ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected both.</p>
            <p>At Day-break,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> a Party of about 3000 <hi>Janiſaries</hi> on Horſe-back advanc'd along the <hi>Danube</hi> ſide by the hot Baths, to throw themſelves into the Town, by the way of the lower Town, to which purpoſe they brought with them ſome Engines like Ladders, made with Boards, which they apply'd to the Wall, and about ſix <hi>Turks</hi> paſs'd, who were cut off by thoſe on the inſide. About 400 rid along the Wall of the lower Town, till they came to <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Valley, receiving the Fire of our Lines, which was there doubled upon them; and a little further, they met ſome Squadrons of Horſe, who cut them all off except four or five, who got into the Town. They were ſo confounded with our Lines and Redoubt, and by ſeeing Enemies on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57370:20"/>all ſides, they knew not whither to turn; ſome run into the General's Quarters, and thought to ſave themſelves in the Tents, the reſt of the Party ſeeing this ill Succeſs retreated. We took ſome Priſoners, and 18 Standards. General <hi>Mercy</hi> was in this Action dangerouſly cut in the Head and Shoulders, which was our greateſt loſs. About an hour after this Action, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had News, that the Enemy deſcended into the Plain, and that a ſtrong Party appear'd behind the Hills, where we beat them the 14th. While they were giving this Account to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we diſcover'd 25 Squadrons of <hi>Scherffenberg</hi>'s Men ready to paſs the Bridge, upon which a Meſſenger was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd to haſten their march, while we prepar'd to meet the Grand Viſier; but whether the acceſſion of thoſe new Troops diſcourag'd them, or that they deſign'd only to amuſe us, they return'd to their Poſt on the Hills, and we lay that Night with leſs apprehenſion than we had for ſeveral days before. Moſt of the <hi>Turks</hi> that were kill'd this day, had about them a Paper from the Grand Viſier to the Baſſa, to give a certain Sum of mony to every one that ſhould get into the Town.</p>
            <p>The reſt of Count <hi>Scherffenberg</hi>'s Troops arrived,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> being three Regiments of Foot, and two of Horſe, beſides ſome <hi>Hungarians.</hi> They encamp'd with their Body on our Right upon the Hills which overlook the lower Town. A great Council of War was now held, where it was debated, Whether we ſhould advance towards the Enemy, leaving a ſufficient Number to defend our Trenches, or attend them in our Lines, and continue the Siege? The later was at length reſolv'd, and our Guards in the Trenches were ſtrengthned out of the new Men.</p>
            <p>We continued our Preparations for the general Aſſault,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57370:20"/>and wrought at a Gallery in the Ditch that was to guide to the Breach. That Night the Camp was alarm'd with the Enemies advancing, and all were on Horſe-back, but it prov'd but a Rumor.</p>
            <p>All things continued quiet in the Camp,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Sept. 1."/> while due proviſion was making for the Aſſault the next day, which was to be on both the Attacques.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> before Day-break,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> order'd the Trenches ſhould be fill'd with ſuch Men as he had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the Aſſault, that the Enemy might not by their motions diſcover our Deſign. They lay very quiet till the Cannon had broke many of the Paliſadoes, and the Signal for the Aſſault was given, which was by 3 Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges of ſix pieces of Cannon from the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abe</hi>'s Hill; It begun about 3 in the Afternoon under the direction of Duke of <hi>Croy</hi> and <hi>Thenock</hi> the <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> General, the Soldiers going on with great courage and in good order, ſoon reach'd the Paliſadoes, and took a Poſt on the Flank of the Enemy which Rak'd the inſide of them, and chaſed the <hi>Turks</hi> from thence, where finding no Retrenchments as was expected, perſued their advantage, making great ſlaughter as they went. Such as eſcap'd fled to the Caſtle, where they put out a White Flag. This is the Account of our ſucceſs on this ſide; But the <hi>Bavarians</hi> (who ſomwhat later began their Attaque,) met with different Fortune, for they were repuls'd with loſs; Nor was it indeed poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to have enter'd that way; However the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> would not permit the Duke of <hi>Croy</hi> to treat with thoſe who Fled into the Caſtle. Leaving them to his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoral Highneſs's diſpoſal, (it being his Attacque,) who gave them Quarter. They were in number about 200, amongſt which was a Baſſa who was a Sub-Governor, his name was <hi>Abdi Baſſa,</hi> the Viſier or Principal Governor
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57370:21"/>dying gallantly upon the Breach. On the <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſide the Aga of the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> fought bravely. There were taken of all ſorts betwixt 4 and 5000, and kill'd about 3000. The ſlaughter was leſs than expected, for though both Women and Children were kill'd in the heat, yet there was more Quarter than uſual from the ſeverity of the <hi>Germans,</hi> eſpecially in places taken by Storm.</p>
            <p>'Tis remarkable, that this Glorious Succeſs of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Arms was attended with a ſingular Circumſtance of Divine Providence, namely, that while our Army march'd with doubtful ſucceſs to the Aſſault of the moſt important Frontier Poſt of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, the Grand Viſier ſhould with a greater Body of Men ſtand a tame Spectator of the iſſue of this Action, and then retire, which they did with great Precipitation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JACOB RICHARDS.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="announcement_of_forthcoming_publication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57370:21"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Plan <hi>herein-mentioned, being large, could not poſſibly be finiſhed with the Journal, but being now under the Engravers hands, you may expect it, when perfected.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
